hello elizabeth good good evening for
you good morning for me
and we're 12 hours apart now um we used
to live on the same island
it's such a pleasure to finally
reconnect after
um a few years now and um
welcome to this the series which is
called voices of the regeneration
and i feel that your work has been a
real
bedrock for this
new way of thinking about us as one
species
in life's evolutionary journey life as a
planetary process creating conditions
conducive to life you've
you've been a voice um initially
not listened to by the mainstream and
and i think
um increasingly people will find your
work as as really
foundational to what is now emerging as
a response to
um humanity waking up to the fact that
we can't go on
like we currently are steering our way
towards towards climate cataclysm
and um more disharmony in our species
right at that point where we need to
come together as one species
understand that we need to take care of
our mother this planet
and otherwise we might not have a future
and
our mother will go on without us so so
wonderful to
be back in touch with you and i normally
start this series
by inviting people to tell a little bit
about their own story how they get
into this got into this work and um you
know
over 80 so this is a
long life here looking back back towards
what got you into studying biology
and what triggered you to
to some extent leave the path of a
conventional scientist within the
academic institutions
and and find your own path that also
took you
to the relationship between biology and
design you pioneered a lot of things
that other people are famous for
so um i'd be yeah
over to you tell us a little bit about
your story thank you so much
daniel and aloha mai kakou
from hawaii everyone that means uh
loving greetings to you all
aloha mai kakou the people
um yes i grew up in the hudson valley
the hudson river valley
in new york state in the united states
which the indigenous people
call part of north america turtle island
in fact north and south america are the
turtle islands
and um anyway i was allowed to run free
in nature
as a small child and only coming back
you know at the end of the day for
supper kind of thing
and so i i was uh total friends with all
the little creatures
of the forest and and on the river banks
i
say i have the mud of the hudson river
still between my toes
and this got me very interested in
nature as a whole and my mother really
promoted that love of nature
and gardening she did a lot of gardening
and growing vegetables
and it was also a time still in the
great depression
when everyone in my culture was feeding
each other
on organic food that they grew on their
own farms
and so everything about my life was very
very closely tied to nature
and so uh i wanted to as i as i grew
up to i guess in seventh grade i was
thrilled to have a biology course and i
realized that
that studying biology would would help
me really understand who are we humans
where did we come from when we are going
where are we headed not knowing those
were the great philosophical questions
of the ages
uh i was asking them already as a child
and in seventh grade i was i was very
young i was only about 10 or 11 years
old i think
as i skipped a few grades in school and
uh so i i had a wonderful biology
teacher and then my parents said but
science is for boys not for girls and
you have our talent so they made me go
to an art school first
but eventually i got myself into the
study of science
and learned the traditional darwinian
version of
evolution biology and then that became
too tight a suit for me i went all the
way through to a phd
and then did a postdoctoral fellowship
at the museum of natural history in new
york
uh studying brain evolution and uh
and and i just began to feel that the
whole darwinian
suit was too tight for me somehow it
couldn't explain
my experience of nature myself was so
far different
from that competitive dog-eat-dog world
that i was taught in darwinian biology
and i actually left science i gave it up
and i i went into esoteric studies i
studied gergief and mata blavatsky and
findhorn and everything i could lay my
hands on
for a broader world view something
expansion
uh expanding my worldview and eventually
i
i went off to the greek islands to live
deciding i was going to write
novels to explain the human condition to
myself
and then one day in the in the woods on
my little island
a walking stick fell on my arm a stick
insect with
long legs looking like a little walking
twig
and i burst into tears because i hadn't
seen one since i was a child and i said
i still want to explain nature i still
want to be an evolution biologist
and so i kind of started over and i i
had taken with me
some of the newest books by friendship
copra and marilyn ferguson
and uh uh who held eric younch
the living universe the self-organizing
universe
and i just devoured those books and i
had no access to libraries
but by writing to scientists i got
answers by mail and they sent me more
books and articles
i eventually met jim lovelock and and
lynn margulis
as i was taken from my greek island up
to cornwall england for a series of gaia
conferences
and so it went that's the story
basically
so you were you were part of those um
gaia conferences that i think um
goldsmith funded um and that david abram
was there
and and stephan harding and you have one
wonderful
series of symposium i read some of the
proceedings
it really resonates strongly with me for
me it was
less so the the darwinian trigger
although that was definitely there for
me too
um or the misunderstood darwinism that
that was taught in biology when when i
was
at university studying biology but also
the
extreme focus on only what is
quantifiable
and measurable in the convertible into
mathematics and statistics
that drove me crazy when i was a
biologist i was studying marine
um mammals um whales and dolphins and
and elephant seals
um off the coast of california and so
much of the magic just couldn't be
expressed in
p values of statistical significance and
and that that's what
took me briefly away from science and
then i also did
you turn back so you you've
pretty much developed a
expansion or a an alternative
view to how evolution functions on on
earth
um looking at both the the western and
the eastern signs you realize that
there seem to be clear phases in
evolution i would i would love
for you to to explain that a little more
in detail
yes well i i was back in the 70s before
i went to greece i was very interested
in paraphysics and new cosmologies
uh things of that kind through looking
at the esoteric world i got into that
what was called paraphysics
and and realizing that in the western
scientific worldview
we start with the big bang and we have a
a purely material
universe only matter and energy because
those are measurable as you said
are included in reality and and this
whole
uh big enterprise this big bang was
was like a battery that was fueling
everything including life but running
down
so the entropy the running downness of
the
of the universe would eventually wipe
away
even the life that had to struggle up
against
this eroding entropic tide
and then i i found uh people like teddy
goldsmith writing a wonderful
article showing that the earth showed no
signs of entropy
except perhaps what humans were doing to
nature
but on its own nature did what didn't
show over four billion years of
evolution
no sign of entropy and looking into the
easter
garden just briefly come in on that one
because that's something that i've been
thinking of a lot to to reconcile
um what we observe on planet earth and
the the clear
syntropic or negan trophic um role that
life
plays on planet earth with the second
law of thermodynamics and physics
um because i also think that they
probably have a point there it's not
it's not i wouldn't say that the second
law of thermodynamics doesn't hold
but what i've realized is that we
there's one simple mistake that explains
why
those seem to be at loggerheads which is
that the
time scales of physics are just so much
more vast
than the time scales of evolution of
life
on one it's more fundamental than that
uh you see the the four basic principles
or
or the pillars of the of the western
physics worldview
what is it um the strong and weak
nuclear forces
and radiation uh and is it radiation
gravity strong and weak nuclear forces
okay three of those four
uh are really about gravity
and gravity is the least understood of
those forces
you see the whole entropic universe is
based on looking through telescopes
through light telescopes where you see
an expanding universe
you cannot see the gravitational
shrinking of the universe
but there were early people in the 70s
like ben benthoff's book stalking the
wild pendulum have you ever seen that
he was the first one to show a doughnut
model
of the universe and of course before
einstein the british had had
actually sat in their leather armchairs
blowing smoke rings
and talking about the smoke ring
universe because the toroidal form the
donut form
was the only shape that could hold its
own in space
right and it revolved this way around
and also
kept turning itself inside out and bent
off had a cartoon where you stand on the
donut looking down
into the hole and you say oh my universe
started it that's this tiny thing and
it's been expanding ever since
because you don't notice that on the
other side of the donut it's contracting
inward
with gravity in order to radiate outward
again right so the taoists have the most
beautiful fundamental symbol of the two
forces spiraling around each other
right the yin yang symbol when you look
at that you know that they understood
a universe in balance the western theory
of the big bang universe
is a linear model it's not
an a balanced model at all and
i think it's because they couldn't
understand gravity and i have pondered a
lot
about why they have such trouble they're
now
talking about that that gravity may come
from
parallel universes or something if they
just bring it into our own universe
they've got it
right then you have the whole thing
in balance and showing that nothing
deteriorates
there's a constant recycling but now
the biologists of course had to fit
themselves into
the the standard model of physics
because physics had been
designated the leading science and the
rest were all subsidiary
so biology had to show how this struggle
for life can happen against the wash
away tide
and so the darwinian theory was very
much
slanted toward this endless competition
and scarcity but if you looked at nature
you saw so much cooperation going all
the all
everywhere including our own bodies with
what
50 trillion cells that work in concert
with each other
our body function of those cells we're
fighting each other when that happens
we're sick
right so everything you look at
once you you get over the prejudice
of of only darwinian theory you see the
balance and indeed i noticed that the
russians
were teaching evolution biology through
krapat
propulkin's book mutual aid which was
the
cooperative site and then both the east
and the west
politicized this so that the soviets
were asking people to sacrifice their
individuality for community and the
capitalists were sacrificing community
for the individual
and it was very frustrating because if
they only put the two together
like putting gravitation and radiation
together
they'd have a complete view what do you
think
what do you because um well
member of the evolutionary leader circle
and and actually one of the people who
um supported me in um being invited
into that circle um i recently talked to
david sloane wilson
and um he very much is walking that
tightrope of of
being a respectable academic in the
the current system trying to lean
himself out of the window as far as he
can within the orthodoxy of the
environment that he works in
um but what he's trying to do is to
to rescue um out of a misunderstood
darwinism and
and a much broader view of darwinian
selection the
variation selection and
um replication as the basis of
the darwinian process and and then with
this
idea that he developed with eo wilson of
multi-level selection he's actually
bringing in that there are layers of
competitive behavior and at the group
level
um and the group level goes up all the
way to the large group of
the planetary process there's actually a
selection
towards cooperation and and pro
social behavior as he calls it um do you
think he's on on
on the track there or what's he sure yes
and and
and he does it very cleverly because he
he preserves the darwinian struggle of
the individual
against individual until you have a
group
but the way you get a functioning group
is when the individuals stop
fighting each other and cooperate right
so the
the first instance of moving from
cooperation to
uh from competition to cooperation
was when the ancient bacteria who ruled
the earth for
uh half of evolution two out of four
billion years of living evolution only
bacteria
and very competitive and feisty in many
ways
and eventually they got together and
formed the cooperative we know as the
nucleated cell
where the different kinds of bacteria
that were incorporated gave up some of
their own dna to a central library we
call the nucleus
and kept just enough as in the
mitochondria you know
to keep functioning within that
community
but basically gave up their freedom to
be in the community
and then because that cell was new on
the planet it had to go through its own
what i call youthful phase
again being feisty and very inventive in
the
competitive phase and eventually another
billion years go by and they form
multi-celled creatures as their
cooperative
so these are the two big leaps so far in
evolution
then you can fast forward to humans
because we are multi-celled creatures
and we learned in school
you know the life comes out of the sea
and the dinosaurs the flowers and
all of those things uh we learned in
school that
that one that one-fourth of evolution
was what has been taught to people
in in western science as evolution the
rest the earlier three-quarters
evolution was called primeval sludge or
something
but it's definitely the most interesting
part
uh i mean almost every protein in the
world today was invented in the ancient
microbial world
and we are only now learning how much we
depend on that microbial world
that without our gut bacteria and our
skin bacteria we cannot stay healthy
and then
and they're also part of the mechanisms
by which we actually switch
on and off certain genes and change
gene activity and basically what
expresses us
and the formation of new cells through
the integration
bacteria like um as you were saying
earlier like most
most of the cells in our body aren't
even human um
we're walking ecosystems ten times as
many bacteria as nucleated cells
and now we're still there's a total
misunderstanding of the viral
world in in the whole medical system
because the viruses are just as
important to us as the bacteria
and every one of our cells people don't
realize this
our cells are bathed in a liquid that's
between the cells
and they think of them as rivers
floating through these
densely packed islands and every cell in
your body is spitting out
viruses and fragments of viruses
plasmids they're called
like dandruff 24 7 that constantly every
cell is emitting viruses
and the full-blown viruses have protein
coats and have
addresses and are sent up river to where
they should go
and if the wrong party opens the thing
it can cause
problems or if there are imbalances
every traditional medical system again
was about balance
the balance of opposite forces but
western science doesn't know about
balance not
at its most fundamental level it doesn't
know about balance
and so so we no longer have a medical
system in which we talk about
rebalancing the system
even though everyone in the medical
system
knows that the only way to deal with
things like the new pandemic
is to have a strong immune system and
that immune system is run by your
bacteria and your bacteria function
through a viral network of
communications that they invented
i believe and so
that's why we need to get our hands back
into the soil because that's how we
get into contact with beneficial
bacteria that that improve our immune
system
and i i'm wondering have you come across
the word
and the work of um john stewart
a biologist in australia because he has
this
one sentence definition of the
evolutionary process that i think is
very much
akin with with the work that you um
you've been doing
which is um evolution proceeds by
a process of diversification and then
subsequent reintegration of that
diversity
at higher levels of complexity what i
call the formation of community
and then comes the important sentence
that throughout the course of evolution
that
jump to reintegration at higher levels
of complexity
normally happens through the evolutions
of new forms of collaboration and and
yes
which is exactly it's exactly what i
call the maturation cycle
and we understand that same maturation
in an individual human
we expect our teenagers to be feisty and
know it all and competitive and and then
to settle down to be
cooperative citizens of their community
right
i mean with the concept of maturation so
i think it speaks to people
i i heard you speak um about this in one
context
and you actually which i thought was
beautiful the
the way that you keep bringing the
relationship is
that there is this jump but then the
that new entity
goes through a juvenile face again and
and in one place you were talking about
this with regard to
the biggest yeah it's not as simple just
basically let me finish the sentence
briefly
um you were talking about it in the
context of
agriculture and then building cities and
how
the whole era of empires was basically
on the one hand there is this
super organism the city as a as a kind
of um
multi-organismic entity but then
the cities as city-states building
empires
went through another competitive phase
and now
so that would give us hope that even um
cities and could actually evolve into a
much more
collaborative phase um in the future
yes you see when when they only talk
about
always larger group uh
larger forms of organization they miss
that fact that each new form
then has to go through its cycle again
it's like a rebirth when a new
entity forms it's new it's young it has
to start again
and that's why i think the the
maturation cycle helps us understand
exactly what's happening with humanity
and i'm glad you brought up the the
cities as cells because
uh the way to see how much we behave
like the ancient bacterial world is look
out of an airplane at a city by night or
by day
it looks exactly like a cell on a
substrate you see the nuclear hub
where there's a densest uh uh of of
you know the the library and and all of
those functions and then
the pseudopods reach out into the
countryside where the food is brought in
from
through the pseudopods of the amoeba if
you'd like
and so that's very interesting to see
because it shows you right away
that a city unless it has been an
infrastructure built overnight
in china or the middle east and then
people stuck into it
that is not a natural city but cities
that grew up from villages to towns to
cities
are exactly like cells growing and
so this tells me that the cities are
much more important to our human future
than nation states
which are completely arbitrary lines
scratched across
cultures on maps and and have
no bearing on ecosystems they have
nothing to do with the watersheds of
of uh what's it called uh
echo uh bioregionalism
next yes yes so nation state boundaries
completely ignore
bioregionalism which is about watersheds
it's about the areas from the high
places to
where the water flows makes that makes a
watershed
right there's usually a river flowing
through mountains kind of
thing have you come across um the
work of a biologist which is also
credited for being the founder of the
academic disciplines of town planning
and sociology sir patrick geddes
um he he wrote sir patrick geddes
scott geddes g e double
is basically the father of
bioregionalism he he
um taught biology at dundee university
in at the turn of the last century from
the 1800s to the 1900s
and lived in edinburgh um the edinburgh
summer school is part of
of his doings he brought people like
heckle
and um basically international
leading thinkers to edinburgh to have
the symposia in the summer to create
a more holistic uh understanding of of
the world
and geddes has this thing called the
valley section where he where he shows
that cities need to be planted from the
mountains to the sea
in the context of the river systems that
connect the mountains to the sea
and and that that's where healthy city
development really needs to go back to
to be the drivers
of a re-regionalization at the
bioregional scale
so we can match human activities in the
way humans meet their needs back to the
biophysical reality
of the bioregions and the ecosystems we
inhabit and that's that's
absolutely and you know it's another
fascinating thing about living
on islands is that we can see that kind
of the rivers flowing out of the
mountains right you're on majorca and
i'm
in hawaii and the hawaiians actually
did the perfect bioregionalism every
farm
went from the top of the mountain all
the way to the ocean
following streams the streams were the
dividing lines between the farms
so every farm was like a narrow triangle
and each of them had access to the
seafood to the
to the fields where they grew the taro
and and made fish ponds inland
to up as high as where you got the
lumber for building the houses and
things like that
so all the farms were equal in that
bioregional sense and
and this is not competitive this was a
natural
division equitable division of of
uh of land and that was it was called
the ahupua a system
of the hawaiians and so when i teach my
mba students we talk
there there's a strong movement here to
recreate that system
which of course has been completely
messed up by paving the water
sheds and and doing everything with
trying to manage nature in the wrong
ways
and i would love for you to like having
you've now been on hawaii
for what um four years five years
um because i i recently
through work that i've been doing with
the commonwealth secretariat on
on um initiating a kind of
slow process of introducing regenerative
development to the policy maker
makers of the 54 nations of the
commonwealth
we had a gathering at the commonwealth
secretariat last
october and i met the delegation that
came from new zealand
which is was largely a maori um
delegation
and through that i had this absolute
delightful experience of feeling a lot
of
the scientific theories that i've been
collecting and putting together in my
own
work um and also the theories of design
scale linking design how it's all
connected health as an emerging property
of
um at different scales of the nested
complexity we're in
and all these kind of concepts i would
offer them
to them and they would then echo back
from within their own worldview
something that was
constantly in alignment like yeah we're
talking about the same thing but we're
talking in different language
have you have you found that um because
it i'm realizing that
the wisdom of the maori is really the
wisdom of the pacific it's the
polynesian
navigators that that that built a system
that is just
so important for us to learn from i
would love
for you to speak to that yeah well i'm
in love with the polynesian navigators
too
and and uh their chief navigator is
is a friend and uh they sailed around
the entire globe two years ago with no
compass
in in one of these canoes and the canoes
are never
uh solidly hammered together
nailed or screwed or anything like that
every part is lashed to every other part
so that it can be flexible
in a storm on that doesn't break on the
waves in a storm
and these polynesian navigators
had umpteen ways of reading nature to
know where they are
they understood nature so well in fact
that they could not be lost
and it wasn't just the stars because
sometimes for weeks you can't see the
stars
but you know the wave patterns and the
fish patterns and the floating seaweed
and the clouds that form over islands
and
and when all else fails they say stand
tall in your canoe until you can see the
land
they say raise your consciousness up to
where you can see
which brings us to a whole other aspect
of nature that western science doesn't
understand
which is consciousness but i i didn't
want to get quite there yet but i want
to say that
i was a co-founder of something we
called the worldwide indigenous science
network
and we founded this for two reasons to
learn from native peoples their sciences
and to let young native people know that
their cultures did legitimate sciences
uh way back before western science was
born
and and they understood all of these
things about how to get along in nature
and so it's kind of funny for them
to see us white people from the western
world you come along
and and figure these things out right
when they have known them for as long as
they've been around
and i want to speak specifically to the
concept of democracy here
uh there's a very wonderful book by jack
weatherfield
called uh indian givers and that's of
course a play on when we say
indian givers we mean somebody dishonest
who is not going to give you fair
exchange
but he is saying oh but the western
world has learned so much from indians
and we gave it all freely and one of the
things they gave us
was how to do a democracy now the
founding fathers of the united states
were exactly on the turf of the
hodnashoni
indian people native americans who had
unified
six warring nations under a great law of
peace for many centuries that had no
more wars
and had a completely representative
democracy
and uh and benjamin franklin one of the
founding fathers of the u.s constitution
was the only one
who bothered to really get to understand
their great law of peace and their
way their political system and he kept
telling his fellows
you've got to copy this you've got to
copy this this is really good
there was no democracy to copy from the
name
came from the ancient greeks of course
but as we know that was a slaveholding
society that wasn't exactly democratic
women were not enfranchised neither were
the slaves
you know but the haudenosaunee included
everyone women and children and seven
generations
into the future with every deliberation
you make now
if a man wanted to propose war he had to
walk into parliament wearing a skirt
and carrying a corn grinding bowl to
remind people what war would do to the
food supply and the women and children
and so they had no more wars
these things are completely you know we
the only thing that the
founding fathers of the us took from
them was
the balance of powers the tripartite
government
in checks and balances against each
other but they left out women children
in the future
and nature uh which was so important
and so if we furthermore they also
uh put in the vote and voting
is a divisive way of doing a multi-party
system
yes nature has has opposites nature is
profoundly conservative with
things that work well and radically
creative when things don't work
when they how to make something work
that doesn't work
that should be a friendly collaboration
not a hostility between opposing parties
that you vote every year whether to do
this one or that one
you always have to be conservative and
radical
and it must be by agreement so
if we could only have the great law of
peace
we would have a real democracy i'm
saying and they figured it out so long
ago
i've experienced that in in my
apprenticeship in the way of council
with gigi coyle and
and others from from the ohio foundation
where and
really the the way of sitting in council
is not you don't come to a final
agreement that you then put
put to a vote you just hear all the
voices and all the perspectives
to the point that the collective
intelligence the container you formed
with the council
informs everyone to a point that that
even if you
don't necessarily have a one sentence
this is what we've decided everybody
is in resonance and understanding of
what now needs to be done
so very often i mean gigi even tells the
story that in the early
councils with with western mindset
developers and so on
they they kind of never understood
where's the decision
um but but all the indigenous people
said well it's obvious after the council
isn't it
um um but i i i wanted to come back to
something that
i did by the way we reflect that in
quaker meetings
it's a close thing they probably learned
from that
but i didn't know you you created this
organization
um of indigenous sciences but what i do
know is that
you've done a piece of work that i think
hasn't got enough attention and that is
so critical
for the future of humanity and hopefully
it will be re-edited
at a much larger scale the work that you
did with this japanese foundation of
initially bringing eastern and western
science together
and then also running another symposium
where you work with the
islamic sciences and what i love about
this approach is that you from the
beginning say
you're basically appreciating multiple
ways of knowing
without dismissing any of them
but um i think you have this wonderful
image of
of a keyboard um can you tell a little
bit more about that story
yes the one thing that that scientists
uh
physicists all over the world seem to
agree on is that the universe is made of
vibrations
of waves and so it seemed reasonable
to take a keyboard as a as a metaphor
uh for a sequence of frequencies from
low to high or high to low depending
which way you look at the keyboard which
end you start from
and when you when you do that you
actually uh
reflect the taoist view i mentioned
taoism before
because they had a matter energy spirit
sequence
and so i say the low keys are matter the
slow vibrations
it's generally agreed on that that's
where matter should reside on the
keyboard
not in the high frequencies but in the
low ones and as you move up the keyboard
you get to electromagnetic energy
which was considered non-real in western
science until it could be measured
before that it was like a stage show
animal magnetism being demonstrated
right
things like that and so then that came
into western science and we're up the
keyboard as far as what we call
zero point energy that background
vibration
in the whole universe and but we can't
get any further because things get less
and less material
as you go up and in the higher case you
have mind
and spirit and consciousness now the
easter the western ones
start from the matter end as i said but
they get stuck
part way up the keyboard because they
cannot measure the non-physical
vibrations
the eastern sciences and and
philosophies all started at the other
end in a sea of consciousness basically
and slow the vibrations down to get the
rest of the keyboard
so they don't have a problem seeing the
entire keyboard
and i often say when people say it's so
important now for us to raise our
vibrations
don't forget to play in the low keys
because the point of raising your
vibrations is to expand your keyboard
and if you lose the lower vibrations
then you're stuck up there with the
angels
who are envious of of human bodies
which is which is one of the really big
issues in in the kind of spiritual
enlightened circles is that you have
too few people who have an imminent
spirituality and too many who are
talking about transcendent spirituality
losing themselves in kind of belly
gazing and
and yes the connection with them
losing the connection with nature and
really our
job is to bring cosmic love down to our
physical toes not just our minds not
just even our hearts but all the way
down to our toes
we must do this now about the the
different sciences
once i could see that you could get
completely opposite
statements out of a science that starts
at one end or the other
and by the way the quantum theorists
in western physics bumped into
not being able to explain what they were
finding
with the assumptions of western science
that this is a purely material universe
and that you can look at it objectively
and that consciousness
comes out of matter those are all basic
axioms of western science so they
turned to vedic science from india to
explain their own results
and that became known that was the
origin of what we call the paradigm
shift right that we're still working on
so that's why on my first uh symposium
which was funded in japan
by this wonderful uh sponsor um
akio uh oh gosh
and now i can't think his name last name
um
anyway he uh
what we did was invite
people with western phd western science
phds who had made the paradigm shift
so that they understood what the axioms
that they were taught
where were and also what the new axioms
they adopted from vedic science were
and could compare the two and i was
looking for how do we bridge
this gap but then i realized suddenly it
was like an epiphany
why should i not allow both of those and
show the world how one science can lead
you to say
consciousness is a late emergent product
of material evolution
in other words matter gives rise to
consciousness while another science with
a different set of assumptions says
no consciousness gives rise to matter
absolutely opposite views
right and i used to talk about this uh a
lot with
with leading edge you know paradigm
shift kinds of science
as scientists um and so then i said well
let's let's see if we can get another
science
uh to write out their axioms right and
that's how kuala lumpur happened
for uh inviting islamic scientists and
philosophers of science
and at first they were completely
confused what was i trying to get them
to do to write down what
their axiom what were the guardians but
eventually they did it and then we
distilled the three sciences into ten
basic
uh statements so every science has
a world view made up of a set of
concepts because
you can't study nature as a scientist if
you have no idea what is a net what's
nature what's a universe
you must have a fundamental worldview
story
about what it is you're studying in
order to study it
so you prejudice the case from the
beginning but it's the only way you can
possibly have a science
right you can't make a theory if you
don't know what you're making a theory
about
so that so then we had the three and
then i my
the fourth one on my agenda was taoist
science
which i haven't brought into being yet
and then indigenous sciences
would be very important to add and
eventually we might end up with a single
science globally
but i think we must go through the
importance of recognizing diversity
it's part of this whole thing of coming
recognizing that racism is holding up
everything that when you do not treat
everyone in the global family
as a beloved equal other human on the
planet
and see nature the same way so if we
stopped making war
on each other and on nature and we
stopped racism which is
almost a prerequisite to stopping war if
we could get those two things out of the
way we'd be a very long way to a better
world
climate change or not have you have you
done
like the work so far the the the three
sets of axioms have they been written up
is it like
people i haven't i have them as a single
page i can send you
that would be wonderful and is it is it
is there a website that i can
refer people to where they could um
i will post it on my website i didn't
think to do that
and out of the work with islamic
scientists was it with
out of that work that you also developed
this
this project of looking at what would a
new economics
based on learning from life's principles
or how long right because
because uh western science uh was the
materialist science
eastern science was the
consciousness-based science and islamic
science to my surprise
was the science of a living universe
their number one statement is allah
created the universe
their number two statement is and he
told us to study it
to study the living universe and i said
to them you know
in order to put yourselves on the map
you have to
demonstrate that you can do something
western science has been unable to do
and i can tell you right now that they
have no science of economics
economics is not a science in in western
it's it's
it tends to be but it's it's um
it does not have it doesn't have the
same kind of axioms and
and theorems and proofs you know to call
it a science
it doesn't study things the same way but
in the living universe with living
nature as your primary
uh object of study they could do one
because nature's been doing economics
from the get-go
what is an an economy takes resources
transforms them into goods and services
distributes consumes and recycles we do
all of those except the recycling part
right which is the big big flaw
and why we cannot call ourselves a
science of economics
but they could do that and then i say
don't replace western science in your
university
with islamic science teach them side by
side
so that people can see how different
assumptions lead to different sciences
and respect them all until we get
together strongly enough
to maybe be able to do our checks and
balances within a single science
so what what would you say are the
lessons that
as because now finally um i remember
i mean you were also involved in um
helping to create
the guy education curriculum and um
the initial version of the online course
that i
worked with for many years um
and back when we
brought out that course in 2007 or eight
it was really quite heretical in terms
of
the critique of the current growth
economics and and the
the dogma of conventional um economics
and what i've observed in the last 10 12
years is that
it's become absolutely okay
to say that the current economic system
is broken and we need to reinvent the
economic
system and and people in very
conventional settings are
saying that now even all the way up to
the imf um yeah
and and there are all these wonderful
forums where people are the we all
alliance and
lots of others where people are
exploring a
a new economics the work of kate
rayworth and another donut
um what
would you say are the key lessons from
life from biology
and from from ecosystems that we need to
have in mind when we
when we redesign um our economic systems
well i think it's very you know you
can't separate politics from economics
and so this this concept of having a
rule by the people for the people that's
we
that literally is what democracy means
in greek rule by the people
that the people must recognize that we
have to have both conservative that
there's always
you're always seeking balance between
extremes
right and uh and the same thing has to
go for a health care system we only have
a sickness care system at present
which is unfortunately so profitable
that it's very difficult to dent
but it wasn't so long ago that we had an
actual health care system
in fact homeopathy was taught in medical
schools across the u.s not too long ago
there's a statute of hahnemann in
washington dc
four blocks from the white house but the
rockefellers
made all the medical schools in the
country an offer they couldn't refuse
money buildings equipment everything if
they would go
to completely drug-based medicine so we
have to look
into our own history we have to look
back into
how can we achieve the kind of balance
that keeps
that where we don't destroy ecosystems
so that the wrong viruses leap onto us
as lifeboats and so that we make peace
with the micro world rather than trying
to
endlessly commit genocide on it which is
an insanity
and so we have to look to to democracy
and to
politics and to health care and to
education
and to all of these things that we want
and as i said before
if we could get rid of racism and
warfare
those two things then i think and and
establish
a real democracy and i see this
happening in the chrysalis of the
shutdown at present that people
first they elevate caregivers to heroism
not military figures not some big
scientists but
caregivers the ambulance drivers and
nurses and
and the farmers sharing food with each
other as people lose their jobs and the
economy goes to park
that we can take care of each other
again as in my childhood now i'm in
another great depression
again and unfortunately i don't i'm not
surrounded by
organic family farms this time but we
must recreate them as you so well know
and as you're working so hard to do
so i say you know there are many many i
i like
two roomy quotes so much one is why do
you stay in prison when the door is so
wide open
and the other is there are a thousand
ways to kneel and kiss the earth
that whether you are an or want to be an
organic farmer or
or go out and register voters for an
election
or fix computers or write songs or
whatever
makes your heart sing think of how you
can make that contribute to
the world that we all want the peaceful
equitable
flourishing world the thriving world
that we want
and then together i think we can adapt
to
this massive climate change and things
like that
and that we won't have these pandemics
if we have strong immune systems
and come back into balance with nature
so
it really is doable i in in
honesty i believe our populations will
be dramatically reduced by the crisis
because we have waited too long already
however
think of yourself and your children and
your grandchildren
as survivors they are certainly
potential survivors
if we go back to bioregionalism as
you're practicing now daniel
it is the only way to go and
it's doable and i think the whole
cosmos is on our side wanting us to
mature
into rebalancing with nature the
indigenous people we have as role models
but they never had to do it at a global
scale
that is what is new that is what we are
tasked with
and we have things like the internet now
we can do it we zoom like crazy these
days and people like eric whittaker can
can put ever more thousands of people
into the same choir harmonizing each
other
you know these are these are important
things that are tools on our way now
yeah i mean garden too
the the political principle of
subsidiarity of of really
enabling people at
the community and regional scale to make
the decisions that are meaningful to
their future and their children
and all other forms of government
governance being
subsidiary to that in the sense that
they only have coordinating functions
and make sure that there's global
solidarity in this process
that's really the the political
organization that would enable people to
like a lot of politicians talk about
citizens participation but we don't have
a system particularly because our
economic system that actually
enables um true participation and
and and also i always find that there's
a caveat to that which is
if you hand over participation before
you also
engage in a decolonialization of the
mind and
and eco-literacy building then you what
you get back from
a participatory democracy is what the
junk that we've been putting in
um to people for the last 30 40 years in
terms of world view and
understanding of life and you imagine
you mentioned the two to um rumi quotes
uh you yesterday watched a video
of your ted talk in marrakech and you
ended with a wonderful hafiz
um quote uh that apparently is a letter
that you wrote
and do you still remember it um the
happiest
uh the never once in all this time
has the sun has the earth no women
never once in all this time has the sun
said to earth earth you owe me
look what happens with a love like that
it lights up the whole sky
wonderful that's it i know you have a
call now so we
probably have to leave it there but
that's a beautiful place to leave it's
so nice to read oh
my god everyone
thank you have a wonderful evening bye
thank you daniel
oops